Finding Aid for Republican Party (Mich.). State Central Committee Records ca. 1958-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Republican Party (Mich.) State Central Committee Records 1958-1979 1962-1978
Republican Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.
85816 Bt 2
Office files and papers of state chairpersons William F. McLaughlin, Arthur Elliott and Elly Peterson, executive director Jerry Roe, public relations director Hugh Humphrey, and Joseph Hunting, executive director of the Republican State Finance Committee. The principal series in this record group include: Annual reports/Executive Committee meetings; Chairperson's files; Staff/Departments; Topical Files; Campaign Files; Convention Files; Miscellaneous; Sound Recordings; and Photographs.
71 linear feet
57.3 GB (online)
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were donated by the Republican State Central Committee (donor no. 6293 ) in 1979 and by state chairman William McLaughlin (donor no. 6270 ) also in 1979. A small group of records was donated by executive director Jerry Roe (donor no. 5238 ) in 1979.
The collection is open for research.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
The exact date when the Republican State Central Committee was organized is not clear but it was probably very soon after the establishment of the party in 1854. In the library, there is a pamphlet published around 1856 with the citation "printed by the Michigan Republican Committee." What the responsibilities of this committee were is not certain, but the name obviously implies some degree of party organization and function such as might have been performed by the agency known in 1883, when its membership was first listed in the Michigan Manual, as the state central committee.
For the period represented by the bulk of these records (approximately from the mid-1950s to 1979), the party distinguished between the State Central Committee and State Central. The committee is the policy arm of the party which meets for two day meetings five times a year. State Central, on the other hand, is the day-to-day professional organization of the state Republican party. Functioning as a service organization, State Central acts as liaison on party affairs in the state's congressional districts, in each county, and at the city and township level. The kinds of work performed by State Central depends upon the funds available. Staff includes a state chairman, an executive director, field representatives, and clerical support.
Specific responsibilities of State Central and the state chairman include running state conventions and planning the state party's participation in the national convention; working with and providing training for Republican candidates on the state, district, and county levels; receiving communications from and with the Republican National Committee and the national administration (when a Republican is in the White House); cooperating with the governor or the state legislature on special issues (such as congressional redistricting, legislative apportionment, appointments to state boards and commissions, etc.); developing campaign material for certain statewide offices; finding and encouraging qualified people to run for Congress and for the state legislature; and otherwise acting as the voice of the Republican Party at countless conferences, seminars, rallys, and workshops.
The state Republican Party in the period represented by these records underwent a process of rejuvenation. From 1949 to 1962, Democrats were in the governor's office. The election of 1962 saw the emergence of automobile executive George Romney as a powerful vote-getter and someone who clearly had ambitions for national office. Other Republicans on the scene were his successor William Milliken and, of course, the man who became Michigan's only president Gerald R. Ford. Significant campaigns in the period of this record group include the senatorial campaigns of Elly Peterson and Lenore Romney in 1964 and 1970 respectively, George Romney and William Milliken campaigns for governor, and Gerald Ford's campaign for reelection to the presidency in 1976.
The Republican Party State Central Committee record group has been divided into the following series:
Annual Reports/Executive Committee Meetings - Box 1
Chairman's Files - Box 1-18
Staff/Departments - Box 19-39
Topical Files - Box 39-50
Campaigns - Box 50-62
Conventions - Box 62-66
Miscellaneous - Box 66-68
Sound Recordings - Box 69-70
Photographs. - Box 71
The records of the Michigan Republican State Central Committee (hereafter SCC) consist of files generated over a twenty-year period by the three chairpersons, William F. McLaughlin, Arthur Elliott and Elly Peterson, who served in this period and by different staff members and departments within the party organization including executive director Jerry Roe, public relations director Hugh Humphrey, and Joseph Hunting, executive director of the Republican State Finance Committee. Although an attempt was made to maintain and otherwise arrange the files into series according to the name of the individual or department within the party that created the record, this was not always possible with the papers of the SCC. Thus some of the larger series within the collection, notably Topical Files and Campaign Files, have been drawn from different sources when that source of origin was not apparent or the files contained materials from two or more individuals
Subjects:
Elections--United States.; Republican National Committee (U.S.); Republican Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.; Elections--Michigan--1962.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1962.; Elections--Michigan--1964.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1964.; Presidents--United States--Election--1964.; Elections--Michigan--1966.; United States--Congress--Elections--1966.; Elections--Michigan--1968.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1968.; Presidents--United States--Election--1968.; Elections--Michigan--1970.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1970.; Elections--Michigan--1972.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1972.; Presidents--United States--Election--1972.; Elections--Michigan--1974.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1974.; Elections--Michigan--1976.; United States--Congress--Elections, 1976.; Presidents--United States--Election--1976.; Elections--Michigan--1978.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1978.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.
Subjects - Visual Materials
Cederberg, Elford Alfred, 1918-; Esch, Marvin Lionel, 1927-; Griffin, Robert P. (Robert Paul), 1923-2015; Hutchinson, J. Edward (Jesse Edward), 1914-1985
Contributors:
Elliott, Arthur G., 1916-; Humphrey, Hugh.; Hunting, Joseph.; McLaughlin, William F., 1932-; Peterson, Elly Maude, 1914-2008; Roe, Jerry D., 1936-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Annual Reports/Executive Committee Meetings
  The record group begins with a series of Annual Reports/Executive Committee Meetings files. The Annual Reports are published summaries of activities but only two reports have been found. The bylaws are important for stating something about the organization and function of the state central committee. Of most value are the files of executive committee meeting files. Ranging in date from 1965 to 1978, the files detail the specific actions and development of programs within the party.
  - Annual Reports 1962, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws 1965-1978 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Meeting Files 1962-1963, 1965-1978 (Box 1)
    (material for some years is sparse)
- Chairman's Files
  The Chairman's Files are arranged by name of the chairs who served from 1963 to 1979: Arthur Elliott, Elly Peterson, and William McLaughlin. The largest grouping of files are for William McLaughlin who was elected to the office in 1969. The smallest set of files are for Arthur Elliott and then Elly Peterson. Additional Elly Peterson files from the period when she was SCC chair will be found in her collection of personal papers also on file at the library. Kinds of materials within these three subseries include correspondence, speeches and subject files. The correspondence consists of communications with state, county, and district Republican leaders with words of encouragement and concern. The largest subseries is for William McLaughlin which includes files of communication with the chair of the Republican National Committee, and records from McLaughlin's work with the Michigan Legislative Apportionment Commission in 1971-1972.
  - Arthur Elliott files 1963-1965
    - Biographical (Box 2)
    - Clippings (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Joint appearances with Democratic party officials (Box 2)
    - Mailings to party leaders (Box 2)
    - Memos (Box 2)
    - Press releases (Box 2)
    - Speeches (Box 2)
  - Elly Peterson files 1962-1970
    - Alphabetical file
      (Note: This subseries includes scattered papers from the period before and after EP's service as state chair)
      - Biographical (Box 2)
      - California 1963-1968 (Box 2)
        (file concerns visits of George Romney to California and relations between Peterson and California Republicans)
      - Clippings (Box 2)
      - Correspondence
        - 1962-1963 (Box 2)
        - 1966-1970 (Box 2)
      - Memos and other mailings to party leaders 1963-1969, 2 folders (Box 2)
        (This file includes mimeographed party newsletter)
      - Press releases 1965 (Box 2)
      - Schedules (Box 2)
      - Speeches 1965-1968, 12 folders (Box 2)
    - County files 1963-1964
      (Note: This subsubseries includes questionnaires on Republican Party Education and Training Programs and Materials; vote statistics, local newsletters, and background information)
      - Alcona-Cheboygan (Box 2)
      - Clare-Oakland (Box 3)
      - Oakland-Wexford (Box 4)
    - County files 1965-1968
      (Note: This subseries consists of correspondence between EP and county Republican committees and officials)
      - Alcona-Eaton (Box 4)
      - Emmet-Lenawee (Box 5)
      - Livingston-Saginaw (Box 6)
      - Sanilac-Wexford (Box 7)
    - District files 1965-1968
      - 1st-24th (Box 8)
  - William McLaughlin files circa 1960-1979
    (Note: This subseries also include the papers of WM while serving as vice chair of the party and in other party responsibilities; he became chair in February 1969)
    - Biographical, speeches, etc.
      - Biographical (Box 9)
      - Chairman's newsletter 1969-1975, 4 folders (Box 9)
      - Speeches, undated and 1966-1978, 12 folders (Box 9)
    - Correspondence and memoranda
      (Alphabetically arranged subsubseries were created by the RSCC; those subsubseries filed by date alone were brought together out of unfoldered and miscellaneous portions of the record group as received)
      - circa 1960-1967
        - A-Z (Box 9)
          (includes mixture of other Republican officials, including Dean Doty)
      - 1964-1967, 7 folders (Box 9)
      - 1968-1970, 11 folders (Box 10)
      - 1969 (includes some earlier dated papers)
        - A-S (Box 10)
        - S-Z (Box 11)
      - 1970-1971
        - A-Z (Box 11)
      - 1971-1972 (includes some earlier dated papers)
        - A-M (Box 11)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 12)
        - N-Z (Box 12)
      - 1971-1976, 19 folders (Box 12)
      - 1977-1979 1976, 9 folders (Box 13)
    - Schedules
      - 1969-1970 and undated, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - County files 1975-1978
      (Note: This subseries consists of correspondence between WM and county Republican committees and officials)
      - 1975-1977 (Box 13)
        - A-Z, 9 folders (Box 13)
      - 1978, 5 folders (Box 13)
    - Michigan Legislative Apportionment Commission (Republican Team)
      - William McLaughlin and Robert Webber Files, 1971-1972 (Box 14)
      - William McLaughlin and Robert Webber Files, 1971-1972 (Box 15)
        (continued)
    - Republican National Committee
      - Communications with 1969-1971, 4 folders (Box 15)
      - Communications with 1972-1978, 26 folders (Box 16)
      - Rule 29 Committee 1972-1975, 12 folders; 1 volumes (Box 17)
      - Rule 30 (Box 17)
      - Rules (miscellaneous), 4 folders (Box 17)
    - Issues Committee
      - 1973-1975, 6 folders (Box 17)
      - 1975-1977, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Topical Files (mainly People File)
      - Armstrong, Anne (Box 18)
      - Ballenger, William S. (Box 18)
      - Braithwaite, Joyce (Box 18)
      - Brickley, James (Box 18)
      - Bulen, L. Keith (Box 18)
      - Dole, Robert (Box 18)
      - Edinger, Murel, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Election of WM as SCC chair 1969, 1973, 1975, 3 folders (Box 18)
      - Engler, John (Box 18)
      - Esch, Marvin (Box 18)
      - Espinosa, Janis (Box 18)
      - Ford, Gerald (Box 18)
      - Griffin, Robert, 4 folders (Box 18)
      - McClure, Harold, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Megill, Dixie (Box 18)
      - Milliken, William 1969-1972, 1976-1977, 6 folders (Box 18)
      - Pastula, Dick, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Posthumus, Richard (Box 18)
      - Pursell, Carl (Box 18)
      - Reagan, Ronald (Box 18)
      - Rockefeller, Nelson (Box 18)
      - Romney, Lenore (Box 18)
      - Rosenbaum, Richard (Box 18)
      - Ruppe, Philip (Box 18)
      - Stahlin, John (Box 18)
      - Webber, Robert (Box 18)
      - Winograd, Morley (Box 18)
- Staff Files/Department Files
  Staff Files/Department Files document the ongoing operations and work of the party. Larger subseries here will detail the work of executive director Jerry Roe, the Republican State Finance Committee, and those staff and departments concerned with research and the press. Within the research subseries is an extensive People file containing biographical and campaign material about Republican candidates for office, information about Democratic opposition candidates, and other Republican leaders. A subseries that documents the party's work among targeted voting blocs is "Other Republican Organizations." Here will be found publications, correspondence, memoranda, and other documents concerning the party's work with youth, women, nationality groups, African Americans, and veterans.
  - Jerry Roe (Executive director)
    - County and district files 1974-1977 (Box 19)
    - County and district files 1974-1977 (Box 20)
    - Governor's Office 1974-1977 (Box 20)
  - Ella Koeze (Republican National Committeewoman)
    - 1964-1965, 6 folders (Box 20)
  - Hugh Humphrey (Director of Public Relations)
    - Miscellaneous, 6 folders (Box 21)
    - Alphabetical file (Box 21)
  - E. James Hayes (Director of Public Relations)
    - 1962-1964 (Box 21)
  - Mrs. John (Ranny) Riecker (First Vice Chairman)
    - 1967-1971, 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Mrs. Ross Backus (director, Republican Speakers' Bureau)
    - 1964 (Box 21)
  - Keith Hartwell (director of communication)
    - Memoranda 1977-1978 (Box 21)
  - William Ballenger (director of research)
    - CAPS (Michigan Republican Committee on the Arts, Professions, and Sciences) 1960-1968, 9 folders (Box 22)
      (Note: Files are mainly those of WB with mixture of other party officials)
    - Research systems, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Research Division
    - Vote Analyses, 0.75 linear feet (Box 22)
      (contents not further described)
    - Directories, Rosters, Lists
      - Lists of committee members (Box 23)
      - RSCC staff rosters (Box 23)
      - Lists of county finance chairmen (Box 23)
      - Lists of district officers, 2 folders (Box 23)
      - Lists of county chairmen and vice chairmen, 2 folders (Box 23)
      - Executive committee file (Box 23)
      - Directory of Republican county officeholders (Box 23)
      - VIP book, 1970 (Box 23)
      - Miscellaneous lists (Box 23)
    - County profiles (Box 23)
    - County and district chairmen notebooks 1966-1970 (Box 24)
      (include memoranda, meeting minutes, various mailings, etc.)
    - People file circa 1962-1970
      - Allen, Glenn S. (Box 25)
      - Allen, Lester (Box 25)
      - Allen, Richard (Box 25)
      - Anderson, Loren D. (Box 25)
      - Angel, D. Duane (Box 25)
      - Apol, Bernard J. (Box 25)
      - Arnett, Homer (Box 25)
      - Augenstein, Leroy G. (Box 25)
      - Austin, Richard (Box 25)
      - Axe, John R. (Box 25)
      - Backus, Mrs. Ross (Jean) (Box 25)
      - Baker, Deane (Box 25)
      - Baker, Raymond S. (Box 25)
      - Ballenger, William (Box 25)
      - Balzhiser, Richard E. (Box 25)
      - Bashara, G. (Box 25)
      - Beadle, Frank J. (Box 25)
      - Beauregard, Eugene (Box 25)
      - Beebe, N. Lorraine (Box 25)
      - Bell, Joseph (Box 25)
      - Bentley, Alvin M. (Box 25)
      - Bishop, Donald (Box 25)
      - Blackwell, Robert (Box 25)
      - Bousma, Oscar E. (Box 25)
      - Boyer, Charles A. (Box 25)
      - Bradford, Judson (Box 25)
      - Bradley, James (Box 25)
      - Brake, D. Hale (Box 25)
      - Breakey, James (Box 25)
      - Brennan, Bert C. (Box 25)
      - Briney, James (Box 25)
      - Broomfield, William (Box 25)
      - Brown, Garry (Box 25)
      - Brown, Jim (Box 25)
      - Brown, Robert J. (Box 25)
      - Brown, Thomas, L. (Box 25)
      - Brown, Vernon (Box 25)
      - Brownell, Samuel (Box 25)
      - Brucker, Wilber (Box 25)
      - Bursley, Gilbert E. (Box 25)
      - Buth, Martin D. (Box 25)
      - Byington, S. John (Box 25)
      - Byker, Gzary (Box 25)
      - Carr, Leland W., Jr. (Box 25)
      - Cavanagh, Jerome P. (Box 25)
      - Cawthorne, Dennis (Box 25)
      - Cederberg, Elford A. (Box 25)
      - Chamberlain, Charles E. (Box 25)
      - Conlin, Michael (Box 25)
      - Conlin, Rollo G. (Box 25)
      - Craig, Roger (Box 25)
      - Cudlip, William B. (Box 25)
      - Danhof, Robert J. (Box 26)
      - Davis, Robert W. (Box 26)
      - De Maso, Harry A. (Box 26)
      - Del Rio, James (Box 26)
      - DeStigter, Melvin (Box 26)
      - Dethmers, John R. (Box 26)
      - Diehl, Dave (Box 26)
      - Dively, Michael (Box 26)
      - Doherty, Walter (Box 26)
      - Dow, Douglas (Box 26)
      - Dukes, Clarence (Box 26)
      - Dumouchelle, Barbara A. (Box 26)
      - Durant, Richard (Box 26)
      - Edgecomb, Diane (Box 26)
      - Engstrom, Arnell (Box 26)
      - Ernst, Richard D. (Box 26)
      - Esch, Marvin (Box 26)
      - Farhat, Leo A. and Norman (Box 26)
      - Farnsworth, James (Box 26)
      - Farnum, Billie (Box 26)
      - Farr, William S. (Box 26)
      - Feikens, John (Box 26)
      - Ferency, Zolton (Box 26)
      - Finch, Robert (Box 26)
      - Finegan, Mrs. John C. (Box 26)
      - Fisher, Max (Box 26)
      - Fitzgerald, John W. (Box 26)
      - Fleming, James G. (Box 26)
      - Folks, James (Box 26)
      - Francis, Lynn O. (Box 26)
      - Gadola, Paul V. (Box 26)
      - Geerlings, Clyde (Box 26)
      - Geerlings, Edgar (Box 26)
      - Gibbs, Jack (Box 26)
      - Goebel, Paul (Box 26)
      - Green, Allison (Box 26)
      - Greene, Leo (Box 26)
      - Griffin, Robert (Box 26)
      - Groat, Gustave J. (Box 26)
      - Hare, James (Box 26)
      - Hart, Philip A. (Box 26)
      - Harvey, James (Box 27)
      - Hatch, Raymond N. (Box 27)
      - Heinze, James H. (Box 27)
      - Higgins, George N. (Box 27)
      - Hilbert, Frederic (Box 27)
      - Hobbs, Ruth (Box 27)
      - Hoffman, Quincy (Box 27)
      - Holbrook, Donald E. (Box 27)
      - Honigman, Jason L. (Box 27)
      - Horrigan, Albert (Box 27)
      - Huber, Robert J. (Box 27)
      - Huebner, Trudy (Box 27)
      - Huffman, William (Box 27)
      - Hutchinson, Edward (Box 27)
      - Jacobetti, Dominic (Box 27)
      - Johansen, August E. (Box 27)
      - Johnson, Ernest (Box 27)
      - Johnson, James B. (Box 27)
      - Jordan, Robert L. (Box 27)
      - Jowett, William L. (Box 27)
      - Kapplinger, Lucille (Box 27)
      - Kelly, Harry F. (Box 27)
      - Kennedy, Earl (Box 27)
      - Keydel, Kurt R. (Box 27)
      - Kimball, Jeffrey B. (Box 27)
      - Kirk, Claude (Box 27)
      - Knabusch, Milton (Box 27)
      - Knapp, William (Box 27)
      - Knill, H. Charles. (Box 27)
      - Knirk, Blaque C. (Box 27)
      - Knox, Victor A. (Box 27)
      - Kowalski, Joseph J. (Box 27)
      - Kuhn, George W. (Box 27)
      - Leonard, Raymond (Box 27)
      - Lesinksi, John (Box 27)
      - Licata, Anthony (Box 27)
      - Lindemer, Lawrence (Box 27)
      - Lockwood, Emil (Box 27)
      - Lodge, L. Harvey (Box 27)
      - Lundgren, Kent (Box 27)
      - Lyle, Charles (Box 27)
      - McClure, Harold (Box 27)
      - McDonald, Jack (Box 27)
      - McGoff, John P. (Box 27)
      - McGregor, Louis D. (Box 27)
      - Mack, Joseph (Box 27)
      - MacKenzie, Clark W. (Box 27)
      - Mackie, John C. (Box 27)
      - Marshall, Frederic (Box 27)
      - Martin, John B. (Box 27)
      - Matthaei, Frederick (Box 27)
      - Meany, Edward, Jr. (Box 27)
      - Meier, Victor H. (Box 27)
      - Merriman, Frank (Box 27)
      - Miles, Wendell A. (Box 27)
      - Miller, Allan C. (Box 27)
      - Milliman, Richard (Box 27)
      - Mittan, Raymond (Box 27)
      - Molin, Keith (Box 27)
      - Montgromery, George (Box 27)
      - Moore, Franklin (Box 27)
      - Moore, Jayne Cooper (Box 27)
      - Morrison, Clayton T. (Box 27)
      - Nakkula, Walter (Box 27)
      - Newton, Carroll (Box 27)
      - Nisbet, Stephen S. (Box 27)
      - North, Walter (Box 27)
      - Nunneley, James S. (Box 27)
      - O'Brien, Carl (Box 27)
      - O'Brien, E.D. (Box 27)
      - O'Hara, James G. (Box 27)
      - O'Hara, Michael D. (Box 27)
      - O'Neil, James F. [with George Romney] (Box 27)
      - O'Rourke, Peter (Box 27)
      - Parsons, Donald (Box 27)
      - Payant, John D. (Box 27)
      - Pears, Don R. (Box 27)
      - Perkins, Stan (Box 27)
      - Perras, Clifford (Box 27)
      - Piggins, Edward (Box 27)
      - Pittenger, Philip O. (Box 27)
      - Potter, S. Don (Box 27)
      - Powell, Stanley M. (Box 27)
      - Prescott, George A. (Box 27)
      - Quinn, Timothy C. (Box 27)
      - Ray, Grant Sherman (Box 28)
      - Reid, Clarence A. (Box 28)
      - Reuther, Walter (Box 28)
      - Richardson, Robert L. (Box 28)
      - Roberts, Farrell E. (Box 28)
      - Robinson, David, II. (Box 28)
      - Robinson, Edward (Box 28)
      - Robinson, W. Earle (Box 28)
      - Ruppe, Philip (Box 28)
      - Sackett, Wayne B. (Box 28)
      - Saltzman, Jo (Box 28)
      - Schlee, Stanley (Box 28)
      - Schmidt, Louis E. (Box 28)
      - Seidman, L. William (Box 28)
      - Smith, James F. (Box 28)
      - Smith, Richard G. (Box 28)
      - Spencer, Roy L. (Box 28)
      - Stacey, Lionel J. (Box 28)
      - Stack, Jack M. (Box 28)
      - Staebler, Neil, 2 volumes; 1 folders (Box 28)
      - Stahlin, John H. (Box 28)
      - Stamm, Anthony (Box 28)
      - Stephens, J. Harold (Box 28)
      - Stites, Robert C. (Box 28)
      - Stocker, Dwight L. (Box 28)
      - Stockmeyer, Norman O., 2 folders (Box 28)
      - Strang, DeForrest (Box 28)
      - Strange, Russell (Box 28)
      - Strause, Roy F. (Box 28)
      - Swainson, John, 3 folders (Box 28)
      - Swallow, Joseph Patrick (Box 28)
      - Ten Brink, James (Box 29)
      - Tenerowicz, Margaret (Box 29)
      - Thayer, Stanley G. (Box 29)
      - Thomas, Douglas B. (Box 29)
      - Thompson, Kenneth W. (Box 29)
      - Tobias, George (Box 29)
      - Toepp, John F., 6 folders (Box 29)